first of all i'm wishing say this
there is a death toll which now
stands at five we should note that
is one greater than the number of
americans who died in the attack on
the u s government buildings and mean
guys e over eight years ago
last time an american government building was
overrun by rampaging and violent mob that
led to more than two years of
investigations dozens of congressional hearing
for the people who were killed as
a result of the capitol attack appeared
to have been rioters themselves one of
whom was shot in the neck by
police as she and others attempted to
break into the speaker's lobby just outside
the house chamber as you can see
in this video the most recent casualty
of the mob that the president and
other republicans in sight
added it's capitol police officer brian sick
nick he's a forty two year old
veteran according to reporting are sick neck
was struck with a fire extinguisher amidst
the chaos on wednesday he succumbed to
his injuries last night and that means
the us capital is now the site
of a hummus
side investigation among other things
well we saw it happen on wednesday
was the apparent murder of a police
officer by members of a mob incited
and directed the capital by the president
of the united states who hoped they
wouldn't successfully intimidate members of congress out
of certifying the rightful democratic victory of
his political opponent
we all watched this terrible spectacle unfold
live on tv
the images broadcast were largely not the
most horrifying ones of the day much
of what we saw silly costumes people
taking cell fees and grabbing the speakers
lectern looked kind of like a group
that might even attend the trump boat
parade
but there was something way way darker
more violent more sinister and more organized
happening in that capital on wednesday and
it's time we see it clearly
it's crowds were gathering on the east
side of the capitol in the early
afternoon you'll remember the republican center josh
holly missouri walked by giving any support
of fist bump on his way in
to object to the electoral college results
to vote against pennsylvania feeding their electors
who voted for joe biden
and after the rioters broke and we
got i witness accounts of people marauding
through capitol hill looking for the vice
president for reuters' editor saying he heard
at least three different rioters at the
capitol say they hope to find vice
president mike pence and execute him by
hanging him from the capitol hill free
as a crater
indeed one of the insurrection is erected
a gallows for the news spread outside
the capital
this is a video of a crowd
chanting hang on my pets
both pence the vice president was in
the capital had to be taken to
a secure location because he hadn't failed
to do the thing that donald trump
told that crowd of people that mob
that my pence had to do or
face consequences or face their wrath
here's some more footage this is of
an eight p photographer being attacked as
he covered the riots he gets shoved
around the crowd as it descends on
him eventually
he's pulled to safety by cooler headed
trump supporter luckily for lord knows what
would have happened to them
we're also hearing first hand accounts of
the terror from other members of the
press aaron chef staff photographer the new
york times writes that she was in
the capitol rotunda when suddenly two or
three men in black surrounded me and
demanded to know who i work for
grabbing my press pass they saw them
my id said the new york times
and became really angry they threw me
to the floor trying to take my
cameras
started screaming for help as loudly as
i could don't want to taint people
just walk this point i thought i
could be killed and no one would
stop them
rip one of my cameras away from
the broken lens on the other and
ran away
and then there are the deeply unsettling
images of this guy in the senate
chamber dressed in full tactical gear carrying
plastic zip tie
as damned cause writes for slate those
are actually flex cuffs the plastic double
restrains often used by police in mass
arrests situation
they went into the capital as congress
was counted electoral votes equipped to take
hostages' to physically seize officials and presume
living to take lot
it is entirely possible that there were
people in that crowd looking to apprehend
and possibly harm and possibly murder the
leaders of the political class that the
president and people like mo brooks and
even to a certain extent ted cruz
and josh hawley have told them
have the trade them
and if you don't believe me listen
to them in their own words i
have to warn you this video which
was licensed from a self described civil
rights activist is disturbing
many people are going to put it
that way
i got hurt
don't want to
we will make them had that
yeah
another extremely extremely disturbing video shows a
crowd of trump's supporters trying to force
their way in as officers including one
who is in serious distress or to
hold their ground
death toll from one wednesday's rampage stands
at five leaves offer was killed now
an active homicide investigation to murdered him
with the accomplices might be an number
scale of evil that might have been
done the skill death and destruction that
might have been visited is almost impossible
to comprehend
what would have happened if they hadn't
gotten to nancy pelosi or chuck schumer
mike pence you thing
and this was unleashed by the president
and no uncertain terms let's go back
on december nineteenth down trump tweeted big
protest in dc on january six be
there we'll be wild
speakers at that protest on wednesday riled
up the crowd rudy giuliani called on
them to settle the election by a
trial by combat republican congressman mo brooks
of alabama said it was time to
start quote taking down names and kicking
ass and then donald trump spoke to
his supporters and lead it all on
the table
we're going to have to fight much
harder
and my fish just gonna have to
come through for us and if he
does
that will be a sad day for
our country forgot to walk down to
the capital
we got to our brave
senators and congressmen and women and we're
probably not going to be cheering so
much for some of them
because you'll never take back our country
with a weak this you have to
show strength and you have to be
strong
you hear that threat to mike pence
he's going to have to come through
for us
a mob that went on to the
breach the capital and search for my
pen send me one day and him
while at the same time that donald
trump tweeted that pence didn't have the
courage to do what should have been
done they were roaming through that crap
republican senator ben sasse or of a
brass can report that trump was delighted
by the chaos as it unfolded at
the capitol and the washington post reports
of pentagon stood in the way of
the national guard being sent in to
help
the president incited and facilitated a violent
assault on congress that result in five
deaths including the death of a capitol
hill police officer
he must face legal consequences for those
actions
even though very few people were arrested
on that day we do know that
some of the marauders and insurrection us
are now being apprehended by law enforcement
like this gentleman who put his feet
up at the desk to nancy pelosi
office and this west virginia elected republican
delegate who live streamed on facebook as
he joined the mob struggling for the
capital
i'm not the only professional republican politician
who was there here's former pennsylvania congressional
candidate rick sec home you may remember
as the guy who lost a special
election and twenty eighteen the district trump
won by twenty points also posting on
facebook about storming the capitol
but denied more than forty eight hours
after that mob stormed the capital we
still haven't gotten a full briefing in
the capitol police on what the hell
happened and who is injured and who
was hospitalized and how
everyone is piecing this together from reporting
and video and it is hard to
put the full picture together