of that there should be prosecution against
him but i don't think anybody could
look and say at peach of this
president is is the thing that's going
to help unite and and bring our
country together
today it has joined over and patient
let's talk about an hour to members
of congress congress woman had her cost
you a court and a democrat from
new york congressman adam ten singer republican
from illinois and cars on court as
when they began a win here so
i know you're a supporter of impeachment
the speaker has not yet decided whether
she's going to schedule it should she
schedule it will it pass
well you know i absolutely believe that
impeachments should be scheduled for several rings
several reasons one of course our main
priority is to ensure the removal of
donald trump as president of the united
states every minute and every hour that
he is an office represents a clear
and present danger not just to
at the united states congress but frankly
to the country but in addition to
removal were also talking about complete barring
of the president or rather of donald
trump from running for office ever again
and in addition to that the potential
ability to prevent pardoning himself from those
charges that's neat
with impeached at four and you know
the several republican members of congress who
oppose raising objections to this sort of
find the electoral college would have written
a letter to president elect biden opposing
impeachment here's what the letter says it
says in the spirit of healing and
fidelity or constitution we ask you falling
request speaker nancy pelosi just continue or
average too
peach present dollars i drop a second
time a second impeachment only days before
president trump believe office is as unnecessary
as it is inflammatory they're saying for
the sake of unity forgo impeachment
well you know i think there's a
couple of things one is we have
to understand that what happened on wednesday
with insurrection against the united states that
is what that is what donald trump
engaged in and that is what those
has formed a capital engaged in and
so when we talk about healing the
prom
the feeling is set for it and
in fact requires accountability and so if
we allow insurrection against the united states
with impunity with no accountability we are
inviting it to happen again that is
how serious it is and i do
not believe that that perhaps my
colleagues weren't in that room perhaps my
colleagues were not fully present for the
events on wednesday but half of which
came close to half of the house
nearly dying on wednesday and
if a foreign head of state if
another head of state came in and
ordered an attack on the united states
congress would we say that that should
not be prosecuted should we would we
say that there should be absolutely no
response to that no it is an
act of insurrection it's an act of
hostility and we
must have accountability because without it it
will happen again
there's a concern also from democrats though
that if you're having a senate charlie
can happen in the next ten days
reading the senator only early days of
president vitamins term it's going to prevent
the confirmation of his appointees to the
cabin and it's going to slow down
for half the passage of essential coven
relief legislation
you know i think i'm you know
george i think we need to review
what actually happened on wednesday the national
guard was requested by the dc council
and was rejected we are talking about
and we are hearing about a complete
and utter lack of preparation the chief
of the dc capitol police lied to
have
ministration chairwoman so lofgren about the preparations
of what happened we need to know
what happened and how deep this goes
and if we do not and if
we do not take corrective action right
now we are talking about those same
potentially compromised alison elements being in charge
of the presidency
already during the inauguration and so you
know with with profound respect i'm i
i believe that the president's safety and
the safety of the united states congress
and and the security of our country
it takes precedence over the timing of
nominations and the timing of a potential
confirmations it in a
media danger right now fear confident house
speaker miss was going to move forward
to page one
know i i do believe that we
will be moving forward with impeachment but
again we are working towards a multiple
avenues and i don't i do not
believe that those avenues are mutually exclusive
this is not an either or proposition
this is not either the twenty fifth
amendment or impeachment or you know it
it i'm you know investigating are other
avenues to
or the fourteenth amendment neither i do
not believe that any of these avenues
are competitive with one another they all
out and they all frankly provide their
own form of of relief and they're
only own forms of accountability and so
i do not believe that this is
a question of deciding or debating between
which of these avenues which should
pursue i believe we should take an
all of the above approach carson thanks
for your time this morning
hi everyone to herself novels officer thanks
for checking out baby c news you
tube channel if you'd like to get
more video show highlights watch live event
coverage click on the right over here
to subscribe to our channel and don't
forget to download the abc news that
for breaking news alerts for wash
yes