particular test result is correct you can
still land on a very low number
arbitrarily low in fact in short an
accurate test is not necessarily a very
predictive test
don't people think about math and formulas
they don't often think of it as
a design process i mean maybe in
the case of notation it's easy to
see the different choices are possible but
when it comes to the structure of
the formulas themselves and how we use
them that's something that people typically view
as fixed in this video you and
i will dig into this paradox
but instead of using it to talk
about the usual version of base rule
i'd like to motivate an alternate version
an alternate design choice
what's up on the screen now is
a little bit abstract which makes it
difficult to justify that there really is
a substantive difference here especially when i
haven't explained either one yet to see
what i'm talking about though we should
really start by spending some time a
little more concretely and just laying out
what exactly this paradox is
picture a thousand women and suppose that
one percent of them have breast cancer
and let's say they all undergo a
certain breast cancer screening and nine of
those with cancer correctly get positive results
and there's one false negative and then
suppose that among the remainder without
cancer eighty nine get false positives and
nine hundred and one correctly get negative
results so if all you know about
a woman is that she does the
screening and she gets a positive result
you don't have information about symptoms or
anything like that you know that she's
either one of these nine true positives
or one of these eighty nine false
positives
so the probability that she's in the
cancer group given the test result is
nine divided by nine plus eighty nine
which is approximately one in eleven
in medical parlance you would call this
the positive predictive value of the test
or p p v the number of
true positives divided by the total number
of positive test results you can see
where the name comes from to what
extent does a positive test result actually
predicts that you have the disease
now hopefully as i presented it this
way where we're thinking concretely about a
sample population all of this makes perfect
sense but where it comes across as
counter intuitive as if you just look
at the accuracy of the day present
it to people as a statistic and
then ask them to make judgments about
their test results test accuracy is not
actually one number but two
first you ask how often does it
test correct on those with the disease
this is known as the test sensitivity
as in how sensitive is it to
detecting the presence of the disease in
our example test sensitivity is nine and
ten or ninety percent and another way
to say the same fact would be
to say the false negative rate is
ten percent
and then a separate not necessarily related
number is how often it's correct for
those without the disease which is known
as the test specificity as in our
positive results caused specifically by the disease
or are their confounding triggers giving false
positives in our example the specificity is
about ninety one percent or
or another way to say the same
fact would be to say the false
positive rate is nine percent so the
paradox here is that in one sense
the test is over ninety percent accurate
it gives correct results to over ninety
percent of the patients who take it
and yet if you learn that someone
gets a positive result without any added
information is actually only a one in
the leg
and chance that that particular result is
accurate
this is a bit of a problem
because of all of the places for
match to be counter intuitive medical tests
or one area where it matters a
lot in two thousand and six and
two thousand and seven the psychologist scared
to get your ends are gave a
series of statistics seminars to practicing gynecologist
and he opened with the following example
a fifty year old woman no symptoms
participates in
the routine demography screening she tests positive
is alarmed and wants to know from
you whether she has breast cancer for
certain or what her chances are apart
from the screening result you know nothing
else about this woman in that seminar
the doctors were then told that the
prevalence of breast cancer for women of
this age is about one percent and
then to suppose that the test sensitivity
is ninety percent and that it's specificity
was ninety one percent you might notice
these are exactly the same numbers from
the example that you and i just
looked at this is where i got
them so having already thought it through
you and i know the answer it's
about one and eleven
however the doctors in the session were
not primed with his ingestion to picture
a concrete sample of it that was
in individuals' the way that you and
i had all they saw were these
numbers they were then asked how many
women who test positive actually have breast
cancer what is the best answer and
they were presented with these four choices
in one of the sessions over half
the dock
doctors president said that the correct answer
was nine and ten which is way
off only a fifth of them gave
the correct answer which is worse than
what it would have been if everybody
had randomly guessed
it might seem a little extreme to
be calling this a paradox i mean
it's just a fact it's not something
intrinsically self contradictory but as these seminars
with bigger and to show people including
doctors definitely find it counterintuitive that a
test with high accuracy can give you
such a low predictive value
we might call this a vertical paradox
which refers to facts that are proven
to be true but which nevertheless can
feel false when faced a certain way
it's sort of the softest form of
a paradox saying more about human psychology
than about logic the question is how
we can combat this
where we going with this by the
way is it i want you to
be able to look at numbers like
this and quickly estimate in your head
that it means to predict the value
of a positive test should be around
one in eleven or if i change
things and asked what if it was
ten percent of the population who had
breast cancer you should be able to
quickly turn around and say that the
final in
after would be a little over fifty
percent or if i said imagine a
really low prevalence something like zero point
one percent of patients having cancer you
should again quickly estimate that the predictive
value of the test is around one
in a hundred that one in a
hundred of those with positive test results
in that case would have cancer
or let's say we go back to
the one percent prevalence but i make
the test more accurate i tell you
to imagine the specificity is ninety nine
percent there you should be able to
relatively quickly estimate that the answer is
a little less than fifty percent the
hope is that you're doing all of
this with minimal calculations in your head
for the goals of quick calculations might
feel very different from the goals of
addressing whatever misconception underlies this paradox but
they actually go hand in hand let
me show you what i mean on
the state of addressing misconceptions what would
you tell to the people in that
seminar who answered nine and ten what
fundamental misconception are they reviewing
what i might tell them is that
in much the same way that you
shouldn't think of tests as telling you
deterministic early whether you have a disease
you shouldn't even think of them as
telling you your chances of having a
disease instead the healthy view of what
test do is it they update your
chances
in our example before taking the test
the patient's chances of having cancer were
one in a hundred in basie in
terms we call this the prior probability
the effect of this test was to
update that prior almost an order of
magnitude up to around one and eleven
the accuracy of a test is telling
us about the strength of this updating
it's not telling us the final answer
what does this have to do with
quick approximations well
a key number for those approximations is
something called the base factor in the
very act of defining this number serves
to reinforce the central lesson about reclaiming
what it is the tests do you
think one of the things that makes
tested his dick's so very confusing is
it there are at least four numbers
that you'll hear associated with them for
those with the disease there's
insensitivity in the false negative rate and
then for those without there's the specificity
in the false positive rate and none
of these numbers actually tell you the
thing you want to know luckily if
you want to interpret a positive test
result you can pull out just one
number to focus on from all this
take the sensitivity divided by the false
positive rate in other words how much
more
we're likely are you to see the
positive test result with cancer versus without
in our example this number is ten
this is the base factor also sometimes
called the likelihood ratio
a very handy rule of thumb is
to update a small pryor or at
least to approximate the answer you simply
multiply it by the base factor so
in our example where the prior was
one in a hundred you would estimate
that the final answer should be around
one in ten which is in fact
slightly above the true correct answer so
based on this rule of thumb if
i asked you what would happen if
the prior from her example was instead
one in a thousand you could quickly
estimate that the effect of the test
should be to update those chances to
around one in a hundred and in
fact take a moment to check yourself
by thinking through a sample population in
this case you might picture ten thousand
patients were only ten of them really
have cancer
and then based on that ninety percent
sensitivity we would expect nine of those
cancer cases to give true positives
and on the other side and ninety
one percent specificity means that nine percent
of those without cancer are getting false
positives so we'd expect nine percent of
the remaining patients which is around nine
hundred to get false positive results here
with such a low prevalence the false
positives really do dominate the true positives
so the probability that
a randomly chosen positive case from this
population actually has cancer is only around
one percent just like the rule of
thumb predicted
now this rule of thumb clearly cannot
work for hire priors for example they
would predict that a prior of ten
percent gets updated all the way to
one hundred percent certainty that can't be
right in fact take a moment to
think through what the answer should be
again using a sample population maybe this
time we picture ten out of a
hundred and having cancer
based on the ninety percent sensitivity of
the test we'd expect nine of those
true cancer cases to get positive results
but what about the false positive how
many do we expect there
about nine percent of the remaining ninety
about eight so
upon seeing a positive test result it
tells you that you're either one of
these nine true positives or one of
the eight false positive
this means the chances are a little
over fifty percent roughly nine out of
seventeen or fifty three percent at this
point having dared to dream debate and
updating could look as simple as multiplication
you might tear down your hopes and
pragmatically acknowledge sometimes life is just more
complicated than that
except it's not this rule of thumb
turns into a precise mathematical fact as
long as we shift away from talking
about probabilities to instead talking about audits
if you've ever heard someone talk about
the chances of an event being one
to one or two to one things
like that you already know about odds
with probability were taking the ratio of
the number of positive cases out of
all possible cases things like one in
five or one in with odds what
you do is take the ratio of
all positive cases to all negative cases
you commonly see odds written with a
colon to emphasize the distinction but it's
still just a fraction a number to
an event with a fifty percent probability
would be described as having one to
one odds are ten percent probability is
the same as one to nine odds
an eighty percent probability is the same
as four to one odds you get
the point
it's the same information it still describes
the chances of a random event but
it's presented a little differently like a
different unit system probabilities are constrained between
zero and one with even chances sitting
at zero point five but odds range
from zero up to infinity with even
chance is sitting at the number one
the beauty here is it a completely
accurate not even approximating things way to
frame basic rule is to say expressed
your prior using odds and then just
multiply by the base sector think about
what the prior odds are really saying
it's the number of people with cancer
divided by the number without it
let's just write that down to the
normal fraction for a moment so we
can multiply it when you filter down
just to those with positive test results
the number of people with cancer gets
scaled down scaled down by the probability
of seeing a positive test result given
that someone has cancer and then similarly
the number of people without cancer also
get scaled down this
time by the probability of seeing a
positive test result but in that case
so the ratio between these two counts
the new odds upon seeing the test
looks just like the prior odds except
multiplied by this term here which is
exactly the base factor
look back at our example where the
base factor was ten and as a
reminder this came from the ninety percent
sensitivity divided by the nine percent false
positive rate how much more likely are
you to see a positive result with
cancer versus without if the prayer is
one percent expressed his odds this looks
like one to ninety nine
so by our rule this gets updated
to tend to ninety nine
which if you weren't you could convert
back to a probability it would be
ten divided by ten plus ninety nine
were about one in eleven
if instead the prior was ten percent
which was the example that tripped up
our rule of thumb earlier expressed his
odds this looks like one to nine
by her simple rule this get updated
to tend to nine which you can
already read off pretty intuitively it's a
little above even chances a little above
one to one if you prefer you
can convert it back
to a probability you would write it
as ten out of nineteen or about
fifty three percent and indeed that is
what we already found by thinking things
through with a sample population let's say
we go back to the one percent
prevalence but i make the tests more
accurate now what if i told you
to imagine that the false positive rate
was only one person instead of nine
percent but that would mean is
that are based factor is ninety instead
of ten the test is doing more
work for us in this case with
the more accurate test it gets updated
to ninety to ninety nine which is
a little less than even chance is
something a little under fifty percent to
be more precise you could make the
conversion back to probability and work out
that it's around forty eight percent but
honestly
you're just going for a gut feel
it's fine to stick with the odds
do you see what i mean about
how just defining this number helps to
combat potential misconceptions for anybody who's a
little hasty in connecting test accuracy directly
to your probability of having a disease
it's worth emphasizing that you could administer
the same test with the same accuracy
to multiple different patients who all get
the same exact result but if
they are coming from different contact that
result could mean wildly different things however
the one thing that does stay constant
in every case is the factor by
which each patient prior odds get updated
and by the way this whole time
we've been using the prevalence of the
disease which is the proportion of people
in a population who have it as
a substitute for the prior the probability
of having it before you see a
test however that's not necessarily the case
if there were other unknown factors things
like symptoms or in the case of
a contagious disease things like known contacts
those also factor into the prior and
they could potentially make a huge difference
as another side note so far we've
only talked about positive test results but
way more often you would be seeing
a negative test result the logic there
is completely the same but the biggest
factor that you compute is going to
look different instead you look at the
probability of seeing this negative test result
with the disease versus without the disease
so in our cancer example this would
have been the ten percent false negative
rate divided by the ninety one percent
specificity or about one in nine in
other words seeing a negative test result
in that example would reduce your prior
odds by about an order of magnitude
when you write it all out as
a formula here's how it looks it
says your odds of having a disease
given a test result equals your odds
before taking the test prior odds times
the biggest factor that let's contrast this
with the usual way that pays well
as britain which is a bit more
complicated in case you haven't seen it
before it's essentially just what we were
doing
what sampled populations but you wrap it
all up symbolically remember how every time
we were counting the number of true
positives and then dividing it by some
of the true positives and the false
positives we do just that except instead
of talking about absolute amounts we talk
of each term as a proportion so
the proportion of true positives in the
population
i'm from the prior probability of having
the disease multiplied by the probability of
seeing a positive test result in that
case then we copy that term down
again into the denominator and then the
proportion of false positives comes from the
prior probability of not having the disease
times the probability of a positive test
in that case if you weren't you
could also write
this down with words instead of symbols
terms like sensitivity and false positive rate
are more comfortable and this is one
of those formulas where once you say
it out loud it seems like a
bit much but it really is no
different from what we were doing was
sampled populations if you wanted to make
the whole thing look simpler you often
see this entire denominator written just as
the probability of seeing a positive test
result
overall while that does make for a
really elegant little expression if you intend
to use this for calculations it's a
little disingenuous because in practice every single
time you do this you need to
break down that denominator into two separate
parts breaking down the cases so taking
this more honest representation of it let's
compare two versions of base rule
and again maybe it looks nicer if
we use the word sensitivity and false
positive rate if nothing else it helps
emphasize which parts of the formula are
coming from statistics about the test accuracy
i mean this actually emphasizes one thing
i really like about the framing with
odds and a base factor which is
that it cleanly factors out the parts
that have to do with the prior
and the parts that have to do
with the test accuracy
but over in the usual formula all
of those are very intermingled together and
this is a very practical benefit it's
really nice if you want to swap
out different priors and easily see their
effect this is what we were doing
earlier but with the other formula to
do that you have to re compute
everything each time you can't leverage a
pre computed based factor the same way
the odds
aiming also makes things really nice if
you want to do multiple different busy
and updates based on multiple pieces of
evidence for example let's say you took
not one test but to or you
want it to think about how the
presence of symptoms plays into it for
each piece of new evidence you see
you always ask the question how much
more likely would you be to see
that with the disease versus without the
disease
each answer to that question gives you
a new base factor in new thing
that you multiply by your odds
beyond just making calculations easier there's something
i really like about attaching a number
to test accuracy that doesn't even look
like a probability mean if you hear
that a test has for example eight
nine percent false positive rate that's just
such a disastrously ambiguous phrase it's so
easy to misinterpret it to mean there's
a nine percent chance that your positive
test result is false but
imagine if instead the number that we
heard tacked on to test result was
that the base factor for a positive
test result is safe ten there's no
room to confuse that for your probability
of having a disease the entire framing
of what a base factor is is
it it's something that acts on their
prior it forces your hand to acknowledge
the prior is something that's separate entirely
and how
highly necessary to drawing any conclusion
all that said the usual formulas definitely
not without it's merits if you view
it not simply as something to plug
numbers into but as an encapsulation of
the sample population idea that we've been
using throughout you could very easily argue
that that's actually much better for your
intuition after all it's what we were
routinely falling back on in order to
check ourselves
at the base vector computation even made
sense in the first place
like any design decision there is no
clear cut objective best here but it's
almost certainly the case that giving serious
consideration to that question will lead you
to a better understanding of peaceful
oh
also since we're on the topic of
kind of paradoxical things a friend of
mine matt cooke recently wrote a book
all about paradoxes i actually contributed a
small chapter to it with thoughts on
the question of whether method invented or
discovered in the book as a whole
is this really nice connection of thought
provoking paradoxical things brings
from philosophy to math and physics you
can of course find all the details
in the description
mm
mm mm